Your Highness, I...
二郡主 属下
Please forgive my incompetence.
属下 属下无能
Lin Qi suddenly showed up
林七她突然出现
and saved Chen Qianqian.
救了那陈芊芊
Lin Qi is still alive?
林七竟然还活着
Su Ziying has been captured.
苏子婴被俘
They've run away towards Xuanhu City.
一群人往玄虎城的方向逃了
You good-for-nothings.
一群废物
Send guys to chase them.
再派人去
Make sure Chen Qianqian is killed
一定要在他们抵达玄虎城之前
before they arrive at Xuanhu City.
杀了陈芊芊
Got it.
是
Mr. Pei.
裴公子
Minister Pei.
裴司军
You can leave.
你先下去
Got it.
是
The City Owner has made an official statement.
城主已经公告天下
For the common people in Huayuan City,
对于花垣城百姓而言
Chen Qianqian is already dead.
少城主陈芊芊已经死了
Now that the Princess Royal's legs haven't been cured,
而大郡主的双腿还未痊愈
you'll be the only candidate for Crown Princess.
继任城主 只剩你一个人选
Why do you still not let Qianqian go?
为什么你还是不肯放过芊芊
She's left Huayuan City,
她现在是离开花垣城了
but what if my mother changes her mind
但难保母亲日后不会心软
and allows her to come back?
召她回来
Are you determined
为了一个不确定
to kill your sister who grew up with you
你就要对自己从小长大的妹妹
just for that reason?
赶尽杀绝
In case your mother knows about it,
万一城主得知此事
I'm not sure
我救得了你一次
if I can save you again.
但救不了你第二次
Pei Heng,
裴恒
do you think
你不要以为你在母亲面前
you can make indiscreet criticisms
替我求了情
because you interceded with my mother on my behalf?
就能对我指手画脚
As for flower token,
花符的事情
I haven't got even with you.
我还没找你算账
When my mother forgives me,
等我求得了母亲的原谅
I'll still be
我
Minister of Defense of Huayuan City.
才是花垣城司军
I don't know
暂且不说
if your mother will forgive you,
城主会不会原谅你
but don't forget
你别忘了
City Guards evolved from the army of the Pei family.
护城军和裴家军一脉相承
It's right and proper that
司军一职
a descendant of the Pei family serves as Minister of Defense.
理应由裴家后人执掌
It depends on if you can convince everyone.
那就要看你能不能服众了
I don't think
我不信
a man can hold this position
司军一职
for a long time.
会一直握在一个男人手里
Are you being afraid?
你在怕吗
I swear to God
我韩烁对天发誓
I won't let you regret the decision you made today.
绝对不会让你后悔今天的选择
What are you doing?
你干什么
I want to always look at you like this.
我就想这么一直看着你
I feel your eyes are telling me
我总觉得你这眼神里面
something is wrong.
透露点什么
Thinking of the night we spent in prison,
想起大牢之夜
I can't control my feelings.
总有点 情不自禁
In...
青
In broad daylight, exercise self-restraint.
青天白日的 你克制一点
We'll go to Xuanhu City by way of Weimeng Mountain.
此去玄虎城 途经威猛山
Thinking of what happened in the storage room of the inn,
想起客栈储物间那一幕
I can't help
总是有点
feeling regretful.
遗憾哪
You... Go to Bai Ji if you regret it.
你 遗憾你找白芨去
Stay away from me.
你找我干吗
Sir, my liquor.
老板 我的酒
Waiter, liquor please.
小二 快上酒
Just a second.
来了
Here it is.
来了 来了 来了
Fill it up.
满上
This way please.
这边
Waiter. Hurry up.
小二 马上 快点上
Well.
不是 你们说
If Orange got married to Banana,
这橙子跟香蕉要是在一起
their kid would be
他们生的孩子
Banange?
蕉橙哪
Guys!
三位先生
Why are you here?
你们怎么跟来了
I didn't expect to see you again.
我还以为再也见不到你们了
Your Highness,
少城主
before you left,
临走的时候呀
Young Master Han insisted on taking us with you.
韩少君非得把我们带上
We don't know why
我们也不知道为什么
and we don't dare to ask.
也不敢问
Maybe he's afraid you'll feel bored,
许是怕少城主一路寂寞
so he wants us
让我们一路陪着
to divert you from boredom by telling you stories.
讲故事解闷
Congratulations,
恭贺少城主
Your Highness.
贺喜少城主
You've dodged open and covert attacks.
绞尽脑汁 躲过明枪暗箭
You had a difficult time.
不容易
I'm glad you've survived and come to the final episode.
终于 活到了大结局
I have to thank you for your advice and suggestions.
这多亏了三位先生的出谋划策
I did it by good fortune.
我这也是纯属侥幸
As the saying goes,
有道是 三个臭皮匠
two heads are better than one.
顶个诸葛亮
Actually, I wanted to see you
其实我可是站在少城主
stay with Minister Pei.
和裴司学这边的
You know nothing about it.
你懂什么
The more intense the contradiction is
那少城主跟韩少君
between Crown Princess and Han Shuo,
矛盾有多激烈
the more devoted they are to each other.
感情就有多浓烈
You can't say that.
这 这话也不能这么说
Relationships are complicated.
这感情也是有很多种的
Exactly.
就是
No girl would fall in love with a man
谁会喜欢那个一开始
who wanted to kill her in the first place.
就非杀死自己的人呢
Right.
对
Who else could turn things around
谁像少城主这样
like Crown Princess?
扭转乾坤
The Second Princess
那你家二郡主
was gentle at the beginning,
一开始还那么温柔呢
but now she's...
那不现在也
You can't judge people only by their appearance.
人哪 不能只看外表
Do you agree?
你说是不是
Yeah.
是是是
The Second Princess became like that because of Crown Princess.
二郡主还不是少城主逼的
Hey. Wait.
不不 等一下
You've known everything?
你们都知道了
Apple.
苹果
Orange.
橙子
Banana.
香蕉
No.
不是 不是
When did you know that?
你们这是什么时候知道的
Here is the thing.
是这样的
At the very beginning,
你不是刚开始的时候
you wanted to fix up Banana and Apple, right?
想撮合香蕉跟苹果在一起吗
You planned to give Apple a chance to save Banana,
设计一出美救英雄
so you decided to take Banana
让这香蕉啊
to the Music and Dance Academy.
流落到这个教坊司
Right.
是
When he was bullied there,
然后呢 受人欺凌
you'd let Apple show up
到关键时候呢
at the critical moment
再让这个苹果呢
to save him.
把他给救出来
But that very day,
可是当天呢
you took Young Master Han to the Music and Dance Academy
你就带了这韩少君去了教坊司
and forced him to compete with other musicians.
还逼他与乐人比舞
Um. Look.
那 这这这
The three of us are not idiots.
这我们三个那也不是傻子
The clue was obvious.
这 这不就看出点端倪吗
Right?
对 对吧
I admire you.
佩服 佩服
Your Highness,
少城主
why do you know people around you so well?
为什么对周边的人如此了如指掌
And you know lots of little-known secrets,
而且知道外人很多不知道的秘密
like where Dragon Bone was hidden
比如 龙骨藏在哪里
and how Young Master Han suffered heart disease.
韩少君有心疾
You often foretold things.
经常未卜先知
It's like...
这种感觉 就好像
It's like you live inside a story
就好像是你们都在故事当中
and I live outside it.
而我 却在故事之外
Exactly.
对对对
Could it be that...
少城主难道是
...you're an immortal?
神仙转世
Whatever.
随便吧 随便吧
As you like.
怎么说都行
Anyway,
反正
it's true that Apple is Chuchu,
这苹果的确是楚楚
Orange is me
橙子 是我
and Banana is Han Shuo.
这香蕉自然就是韩少君了
I created this story.
这个故事呢 也是我写的
Someday,
有朝一日
when the three of you
等三位先生进入到
enter the scripts you write,
自己撰写的剧本里
the same thing will happen to you.
处境 也就会跟我一样
In this case,
这么说来
you created us.
是少城主创造了我们哪
Don't say that.
没有
When I go back to Huayuan,
等我回到花垣
I'll write a book about you
一定把少城主的事迹编纂成册
so that your name will be remembered by posterity.
流芳千古
Right.
对对对
Sir?
客官
Han Shuo.
韩烁 韩烁
Hey. Han Shuo. Wait for me.
不是 韩烁 你等等我
Han Shuo, stop running.
韩烁 韩烁 你别跑了
Hey. I can explain.
不是 你听我解释
It hurts.
好痛
On the carriage, you said
你在马车上说过
you'd be nice to me all your life.
会一辈子对我好的
It's just a short time ago and you already began to regret it?
这才多久啊 你就反悔了
If I hadn't heard your conversation,
如果我今天没有听到你们的对话
would you always hide it from me?
你还要瞒我到什么时候
I planned to explain to you
我本来是想到了玄虎城
after we arrive at Xuanhu City.
慢慢跟你解释的
I didn't mean to hide it from you.
我真的没有故意想要瞒你
There were a lot of things
只是很多事情
I couldn't tell you at the beginning.
最开始真的不能说
You framed me on purpose for hurting Su Mu
你故意栽赃我迫害苏沐
to send me into exile.
将我流放
That's because I wanted to avoid the previous ending.
那是因为原来被我写死的人
My mother, Lin Qi and Lu Peng...
母亲 林七 陆鹏
They ended up having a stroke or being killed,
要不就是中风
the same way as I wrote in the script.
要不就是死了
I was afraid you'd also end up like that.
我怕你也会走上我设计的那条路
But later,
但是后来
my mother woke up
母亲醒了
and Lin Qi didn't die,
林七也没死
so I felt relieved.
然后我就放心了
I planned to explain to you,
我一直想跟你解释的
but you hated me so much at that time.
但是你当时特别恨我
You didn't want to talk to me at all.
你根本就不想跟我说话
Why did you want to push me away to Chen Chuchu?
那你要把我推给陈楚楚
I stopped doing that when I realized
当我意识到我自己喜欢你之后
I was into you.
我就没这么做了
You even made use of my heart disease.
我心疾你也利用
I stole Dragon Bone
那我不是偷龙骨
and cured you.
治好了你的心疾吗
You forged a tip-off
你假造密信
and asked Chen Chuchu to catch me.
在陈楚楚面前栽赃我
You already knew it long ago.
这事你不是早就知道了吗
I...
我
You designed my heart disease, right?
我心疾也是你设计的吧
As I said,
刚刚不是说了吗
I cured you.
我治好了你的心疾
It's true,
你是治好了
but it's designed by you.
那不是因为是你设计的吗
Why do I bother to explain to you?
我懒得跟你解释
What's up?
干吗
You're not mad at me anymore?
不生我气了
I'm just
我只是
so shocked.
太意外了
But I finally understand
但我现在终于明白了
why you often lied to me,
你之前为什么总是骗我
why everything I did
我做的事
went against your original intention,
又总是与你的初衷背道而驰
and why you're entirely different
你为什么与我从小
from any other girl I've ever seen.
遇到的每一个女子都截然不同
I once complained that you were heartless.
我曾怨过你没心没肺
I couldn't guess how serious you were about me
猜不透你到底几分情意
and I didn't know when you were telling the truth.
我不懂你身上的真真假假
But at this moment, I can tell
可此时我能分辨
you're into me.
你喜欢我
It's true.
是真的
That's enough for me.
这就足够了
Xiaoqian, I've finally got you.
小千 我终于抓到你了
The complete you,
一个完完整整
without secrets.
没有秘密的你
I like you.
我喜欢你
I'm serious.
是真的喜欢你
So,
那你
are you immortal or not?
你究竟是不是神仙
Try worshiping me and you'll know.
你拜拜我不就知道了吗
Honey, please accept my worship.
娘子在上 请受夫君一拜
It's a wonderful time with fine scenery.
不如趁此良辰美景
How about you tell me
你我夫妻二人把前因后果
the whole story now?
娓娓道来
Screenwriter?
编剧
Just like a storyteller.
就跟写戏的话本先生一样
From the two countries
大到
with different systems
两个完全不同制度的国家
to every tree and bush,
小到一草一木
all those were created by me.
都是我创造的
So, as for who they are,
所以 他们是谁
what they'll do
要做什么事情
and what setbacks they'll go through...
要经历什么大的波折
I basically know everything.
我大多都知道
That's why I knew you wanted to kill me as soon as I came here.
所以我一进来就知道你要杀我
That's also why I could survive that crisis.
所以也就才躲过一劫
So,
所以
actually, I'm just a character in your script.
其实我只是话本中的人
No.
不是的
At the beginning, I also thought
虽然一开始我也觉得
you were just a group of fictional characters,
他们不过就是一堆纸片人罢了
but later, I found each of you
但后来我发现你们每一个人
had your own emotions.
都有自己的喜怒哀乐
I didn't create that.
这不是我创造的
You have real feelings,
这是你们自身的真情实感
just like us.
跟我们一样
How is the world you live in?
你生活的世界是什么样的
Is it like Huayuan City
是像花垣城
or Xuanhu City?
还是像玄虎城
Our world?
我们的世界
In our world,
在我们的世界里
as for if men or women
男人做主
have the final say,
还是女人做主这件事情上
sometimes it's like Huayuan City
有一些时候像花垣城
and sometimes like Xuanhu City.
有些时候像玄虎城
That's a subject for debate,
这本来就是一个争论不休的话题
so I wrote this story.
所以我就写了这个故事
Is it possible
你的世界
your world is also created by a screenwriter?
有没有可能也是一个编剧创造的
Maybe.
有可能
A mixture of truth and falsehood. Who can tell it clearly?
反正真真假假 谁说得明白
Are all screenwriters in your world
你们世界的编剧
as lovely as you?
都像你这么可爱
Yes, in addition,
那不仅是可爱
they're talented.
而且还特别有才华
Every screenwriter
每一个编剧
is concentrated
在创造自己的故事的时候
when they're writing a story.
都会特别地用心
Sometimes,
虽然
there are some flaws in the plot.
有的时候会有点小漏洞
Sometimes, it's cheesy.
有的时候会洒洒狗血
Sometimes,
有时候也会有一些
the leading roles become self-abandoners.
自暴自弃的无聊梗
But overall, a screenwriter loves every character created by him or her.
但是他爱他笔下的每一个角色
Sometimes, they even fall in love with a character.
有时候 还会跟角色谈恋爱
Did you
那你
fall in love with Pei Heng?
有跟裴恒谈过吗
It's a different case.
这其实不一样
You're a hero.
你是男主角
A hero
男主角呢
has to stay with a heroine.
是属于女主角的
The male supporting role
男二呢
belongs to all.
是属于大家的
Did Pei Heng know about that?
裴恒不知道这事吧
Of course not.
当然不知道了
Don't tell him.
不许告诉他
I want to be the only one
这个事吧
who knows about it.
只有我能知道
How does the story end?
这故事的结局是什么呀
At the end of the story,
结局啊
Chuchu succeeded my mother as City Owner.
原本是楚楚继任了城主
The sun and the moon were up in the sky at the same time.
日月同辉 天门大开
I fell in asleep after I wrote that
我也是写到这儿的时候睡了过去
and then I came here.
才来到这个地方的
So, I guess
所以我猜测啊
I can't go back
可能 要等到日月同辉
until the sun and the moon are up in the sky at the same time
天门大开的那一天
and the gate to Heaven is wide open.
我才能够回去
Are you afraid
你是不是
I may leave?
怕我离开啊
Of course not.
当然不会
After you leave,
等你走了
I'll stay in Xuanhu City
我就回玄虎城
and marry 300 concubines.
然后纳三百个妾室
I'll have a different woman every day.
我一天换一个 一天换一个
So, I have no time to miss you.
我哪有时间想你呀
But a year
可是一年呢
has 365 days.
有三百六十五天
How about the remaining 65 days?
剩下六十五天怎么办啊
In the remaining 65 days...
剩下六十五天
None of your business.
你管我
You're leaving anyway.
你都要走了还管那么多
Can you stay with me
那剩下的六十五天
in the remaining 65 days?
你留给我好不好
Qianqian, you...
芊芊 你
You'll stay?
你愿意留下来
I promise. I was talking nonsense.
我发誓 我刚才都是胡说的
As long as you're with me,
只要有你在我身边
I won't marry anyone else.
别人我一个都不要
Judging from the days,
算日子
they must have arrived at Xuanhu City.
他们也该到玄虎城了
Your Highness,
郡主 您说
will Chen Qianqian borrow troops from Xuanhu City
陈芊芊不会到了玄虎城
and make a comeback?
借些人手再攻打回来吧
Chen Qianqian is unruly and self-willed.
陈芊芊这般刁蛮任性
She dared to make trouble
也就只能仗着母亲的宠爱
because our mother dotes on her.
折腾两下
In Xuanhu City, men are in power.
她逃到由男人掌权的玄虎城
She couldn't have a chance to stir up trouble.
能兴出什么浪来
The one who's leading the horse is our young master?
前面领头牵马的是少君
He's leading the horse for Ms. Chen?
少君为陈氏牵马
Is it really okay?
这样好吗
You and I are a couple.
你我夫妻二人
Let's act here the same way
在花垣城如何
as we do in Huayuan.
在玄虎城就如何
Young Master, welcome back!
恭迎少君回城
Young Master, His Majesty and Her Majesty asked you...
少君 城主和城主夫人请您
...and accompanying persons to enter the city as soon as possible.
及随从人等尽快进城
They've been waiting for a long time.
城主已经等候多时
I'll take you to the City Owner's Mansion
我这就带你回城主府
to meet my father and mother.
见我的父亲 母亲
People here are so hospitable to us.
玄虎城的人对我们也太热情了
They're not welcoming us.
先看看他们的热情对的是谁
I used to suffer heart disease.
以前我患有心疾
Such a thing has never happened.
没有这样的场面
Of course,
当然
it won't happen again.
以后也不会再有
Do you know where Han Shuo is?
小姐姐 那个 韩烁呢
Our young master needs to pay respects to His Majesty and Her Majesty.
少君去向城主 城主夫人请安了
Miss, please wait for him in the back garden
请姑娘在后花园与众家眷们
with other ladies.
稍作等候
You called her Miss? How dare you?
你说谁姑娘呢 说谁姑娘呢
She's the Third Princess of Huayuan City
这可是花垣城三郡主
and the respected Crown Princess.
尊贵的少城主
She was.
曾经是
Repeat it if you dare.
你再给我说一遍
Forget about it. When in Rome, do as the Romans do.
算了算了 入乡随俗 来都来了
Sir, please stay here.
这位公子留步
Males and females are treated differently in Xuanhu City.
我们玄虎城男女有别
The back garden is a place for female members of noble families
这后花园是城中贵族家眷女子
to gather together.
聚会等候之地
As an irrelevant man, you can't go inside
这不相干的男子想要进去
unless you're castrated.
得先净身
It's okay. I'll go there alone.
没事 我自己去
Wait for me here.
你就在这儿等我
Xiaoqian, why are you nervous?
小千 你紧张什么
You felt just like a fish in water when in Huayuan City.
在花垣城混得如鱼得水
Why are you like a fish out of water in Xuanhu?
怎么到了玄虎城就不适应了
Life is like a drama. It all depends on your acting skills.
人生如戏 全靠演技
You can do it.
可以的
Her Majesty arrives.
城主夫人到
Lin Qi.
林七
In Xuanhu City, men have the final say.
玄虎城是男人当家做主
So, women here
所以女人在这里比较
are quiet and restrained.
文静婉约
It makes sense.
合理
Sit down.
坐下吧
The feast starts now.
开宴
Your Majesty,
禀城主夫人
she's the girl brought back by Young Master Han
这位就是韩少君带回来的
from Huayuan City.
花垣女子
She's Chen Qianqian.
陈芊芊
Nice to meet you, Your Majesty.
夫人好
I'm Han Shuo's wife.
我就是韩烁迎娶的妻子
Are you Qianqian?
你就是芊芊
Yes.
是
Enjoy your meal first.
先用饭吧
In Xuanhu City,
在我们玄虎城
a married woman needs to look after parents-in-law.
女子嫁人后要侍奉公婆
When Her Majesty is having a meal,
城主夫人用饭
you need to distribute the foods for her.
您应当从旁布菜
Filial piety is the foundation of all virtues.
百善孝为先
I should do that.
应当
Young Master Han won't leave now that he's back, right?
少君这次回来他就不走了吧
I heard that his heart disease has been cured.
听说呀 他心疾已经治愈
He doesn't need to marry into Huayuan City, right?
该不会再入赘花垣城了吧
That was a lie in the first place.
本来就是骗人的
As a man, how can he marry into another family?
男子汉大丈夫 入什么赘呀
I heard women had the final say in Huayuan City.
听说花垣城是女子当家
That's unacceptable.
那怎么行啊
I heard
听说呀
Chen Qianqian claimed to be a princess of the first rank.
这陈芊芊号称三公主
It seems
这名声啊
she has a bad reputation.
可不怎么好听呢
She's unreasonable and ridiculous.
蛮不讲理 荒唐无度
She's even illiterate.
还目不识丁呢
Rumors are fiercer than tigers.
传闻猛如虎啊
What to do
万一韩烁母亲也误会我
if Han Shuo's mother misunderstands me too?
可怎么办啊
Your Majesty.
夫人
You're clever.
你倒是聪慧
I'm expert at food.
吃这一方面 我在行
Good.
好
Tell me what else you like to do at ordinary times.
说说 平时还爱干什么
Nothing special.
没干什么
I've been learning poetry at clan school since childhood.
自小 在宗学堂学习诗词
I help my mother deal with public affairs when I'm available.
平时啊 就帮母亲处理处理政务
Sometimes,
偶尔呢
I discuss poetry and prose with my sisters.
跟姐妹们一起谈谈诗词歌赋
On the spur of the moment,
这兴致一来
I'll go hunting in the mountains.
我就上山去骑射围猎
I'll play the game of go with my teacher when I'm tired.
累了就与先生手谈两局
When I'm in the streets, I'll help those in need.
逛街的时候 帮扶老幼病残
Once the common people are in trouble,
百姓一有难
I'll lead troops to clean up bandits in the mountains.
我立刻就带兵上山 清剿山匪
I want to try my best
尽我所有的力气
to be a qualified Crown Princess.
做好少城主
Do you have a sense of shame or not?
你要不要脸呀
That's right.
没错
The Third Princess is deeply respected
三公主在花垣城
by the common people in Huayuan.
确实深受百姓们的爱戴
Lack of talent in a woman is a virtue.
女子无才便是德
In Xuanhu City,
我们玄虎城女子
what a woman should avoid most is to be seen in public.
最忌讳不安于室
You call that "to be seen in public"?
这就叫不安于室了
Is there anything even worse?
难道还有更过分的
She used to go to the Music and Dance Academy eight times a day.
她以前一天要去八趟教坊司
It's...
这 这
Um. It's not like what you thought.
不 不是你们想的那样的
The Music and Dance Academy is run by my family.
教坊司是我家开的
It's conservative.
特别保守
Can you keep silent?
你能不能别说了
Shuo, you must have had a rough time.
我儿此行辛苦
Has your heart disease been cured?
心疾已经痊愈了
Father,
回父亲
it has.
已经痊愈
That's great.
甚好
Besides having your heart disease cured,
在花垣你除了治愈心疾
what else have you done?
还做了些什么
To get rid of Huayuan's Crown Princess, Chen Qianqian,
除掉花垣城继承人陈芊芊
assassinate Huayuan's City Owner
刺杀花垣城主
and exploit the situation to conquer Huayuan
趁势收服花垣
and occupy the black stone mine?
将乌石矿收入玄虎囊中
You had planned to do all those things before you left,
临走的时候你做的这一切计划
but you ended up doing none of them.
一个都没完成
I don't want to make things difficult for you.
为父也不为难你
You didn't kill Chen Qianqian,
你不杀陈芊芊
Huayuan's City Owner
不杀花垣城主
or any of the common people there.
不杀花垣百姓
I understand why you made the decision and I agree to it.
这我都理解 也赞同
I just want to ask you
我就想问问你
why you didn't get the mine.
这矿呢
Oh my god. What are you doing?
我的姑奶奶 你说这干吗呢
I'm going back to Huayuan.
回花垣
We can't.
不能回呀
The Second Princess wants to kill you.
二郡主等着杀你呢
I know.
我知道
I made this decision after careful consideration.
这也是经过我深思熟虑之后的
Now that conditions are tough at both places,
既然两边生存环境都这么恶劣
why don't I choose the one
我为什么不选个
where I'm happier?
让自己开心点的地方
Am I right?
对不对
You still want to be comfortable and happy?
还舒服还开心
You're so careless.
你心可真大啊
You want to die?
你不要命了
Do you think I can survive if I stay here?
你以为我留在这儿就有命吗
If you want to go back to your hometown,
少君夫人要回娘家
you need to copy "Female Virtues" 100 times
需先将女德抄写百遍
and be familiar with the rules.
熟了规矩才能回去
It's so hard for me!
我 我太难了
What's up?
怎么了
Don't you know that?
还怎么了
People in Xuanhu
你们玄虎城的人
give Crown Princess their attitude.
可没给我们少城主好脸色看
She also needs to follow "Three Obedience", "Four Virtues" and "Seven Grounds for Divorce".
还要遵从什么三从四德七出
If she violates any of them,
但凡有一条不合
you'll divorce her.
你就得把我们少城主给休了呀
She is even requested to copy it 100 times.
还让抄写一百遍呢
How could it be like that?
竟有这事
It's always been the case in our city.
城中规则向来如此
Why can't Young Master's wife obey them?
怎么少君夫人就不能遵守呢
See?
你听听
I'll do it.
我抄
You'll get a divorce in the following cases: you're not obedient to the in-laws;
不顺父母者出
you fail to have a female heir...
膝下无女者出
Oh, no.
不对啊
You fail to have a male heir, now that we're in Xuanhu.
在玄虎城是膝下无子者出
You can leave.
你们下去吧
I'll be here.
这里有我就够了
Madam, please serve our young master.
请少君夫人服侍少君
What are you doing?
你干什么
In Xuanhu City,
在玄虎城
men are superior.
以男子为尊
It's against rules.
这不合规矩啊
Yeah.
是啊
But in my mind,
但在我心里
you're always superior.
夫人为尊
How do you like it? Is the water hot?
怎么样 水温还行吗
Enough.
干吗
They've left. Stop it.
人都走了 还不松开
Sorry for letting you suffer wrong.
让你受委屈了
Are you unhappy?
是不开心了吗
You're so nice.
是你太好了
Do you still want to go back?
那你还要回娘家吗
No.
不回了
I don't want to leave you alone.
我不想扔下你一个人
You were supposed to do lots of things in Huayuan,
你这回到花垣走了一遭
but you didn't do any of them
什么事都没办成
and even came back with a burden like me.
还带上了我这个拖油瓶
Did your father make things difficult for you?
父亲有没有为难你啊
It's just Xuanhu City.
不就是玄虎城吗
It's just a big tiger.
不就是大老虎吗
No big deal. I have thorns.
那我陈小千还有刺呢
Right.
是
You're the most powerful.
你最厉害
Your Majesties.
城主 城主夫人
How is it going with Han Shuo?
少君那边什么情况
Young Master...
少君
He's...
少君那边
Go ahead!
说
He's washing the feet of the woman from Huayuan City.
少君竟给花垣城的女人 洗脚
Ridiculous.
岂有此理
As a man,
堂堂七尺男儿
how can he humiliate himself?
怎么会向一介妇人低头
He's even washing her feet.
还给她洗脚
Is it hot?
烫吗
No.
不烫
Your Highness.
二郡主
Your Highness, please go back.
二郡主请回吧
Her Majesty is having a rest.
城主 正在休息
Please come here tomorrow.
等明日再来
My mother is not very well in health.
母亲身体欠安
It's justified that she has to have more rest.
自然该多休息
In the coming days,
往后
I'll come and see her every day.
我日日都会来向母亲问安
I hope she'll get better as soon as possible.
希望母亲身体 早日康健
You're a dutiful daughter.
二郡主孝顺
Let's go to the campsite.
去营地
Your Highness,
郡主
Mr. Pei has taken office as Minister of Defense.
裴公子已经正式上任司军一职了
We...
我们
I'd like to see how he's doing there.
我去会会这位裴司军
Mr. Pei, what should we do
司军 玄虎城的战俘
with prisoners of war from Xuanhu City?
应该如何处置
Kill them.
杀了
Your Highness.
二郡主
you don't hold any official post in the army.
如今你无任何军职
Now that you came here without permission,
擅闯军营
you deserve to be punished according to the military law.
当依军法处置
I'm afraid you're lack of experience,
我怕你这个裴司军没有什么经验
so I'm here to give you some advice.
所以特意过来帮帮你
People of Xuanhu are sinister and insidious.
玄虎人阴险狡诈
They've been coveting
一直觊觎我花垣城的
our black stone mine and black water mine.
乌石矿和黑水矿
As for them,
他们的人
we should wipe them off the face of the earth.
当然要斩草除根
Your Highness,
那敢问二郡主
who do you think deserve to be killed,
背信弃义的人
those who act in bad faith
和忠心耿耿的人
or those who're faithful and true?
哪种人更该死
What do you mean?
你什么意思
We fought Xuanhu City Guards
我们与这些玄虎护城军
because we serve different masters.
只不过是立场不同
They were just under orders to attack us.
他们只是听令攻打我们
I don't think they deserve to die.
在我看来 罪不至死
I'll let them do physical work in the mines.
我会安排他们到矿山劳作
You made such a big mistake,
而你犯下那样大的过错
but the City Owner forgave you
城主都能宽宏大量
and gave you a chance to correct it.
给你一个机会
Why can't you
你为何不能
give them a chance to survive?
给他们一个生还的机会
You're a man.
你一个男人
You know nothing about war.
懂什么是两城相争
It's a life-or-death struggle
玄虎和花垣
between Xuanhu and Huayuan.
向来都是你死我活的关系
To be merciful to your enemies
对敌人心慈手软
is to be cruel to yourself.
就是对自己残忍
If you let them survive,
你放他们走
you're laying by trouble for the future.
就是放虎归山
Sooner or later,
迟早有一日
you'll be killed by them.
他们会要了你的命
I'm Minister of Defense.
如今我是司军
As for how to deal with prisoners of war,
该如何处置战俘
it's up to me.
我定
I hope
那就要问问
you can convince your subordinates.
你能不能服众了
The late Minister Pei
已故的裴司军
once said,
曾经说过这样一句话
as for war, pugnacity was the only virtue
战争总是以好斗为美
and pacifism was the only vice.
以求和为耻
Did you hear that?
听见了吗
That's what Minister of Defense should be like.
这才是一个司军该有的样子
She also said
裴司军的后半句是
only those who were really brave
然而 只有真正的勇者
could stay rational and end hostilities.
才能保持理智 结束战斗
To stop use of weapons and avoid war is truly military.
所谓止戈为武
Mr. Pei is of a kindly disposition. He's brave and persistent.
裴公子宅心仁厚 勇敢坚毅
He's quite like his mother as for demeanor.
颇有已故裴司军的遗风
Mr. Pei, we're willing to follow you.
属下愿听令裴司军
Books!
卖书了 卖书了
Newly published books.
新鲜出炉的
"The Rumored Third Princess".
传闻中的三公主
The Third Princess...
三公主
Sir,
老板
is there any book about the Third Princess and Minister Pei?
有没有讲三公主跟裴司军的书
Yes. Sure.
有 全都有
There is also some inside information
还有三公主和二郡主
about the Third Princess and the Second Princess falling out.
姐妹反目的内部消息呢
It's wonderful.
可精彩了
Pitifully, the Second Princess won in the end.
可惜最后是二郡主赢了
I like the Third Princess better.
我还是喜欢三公主
Me too.
谁不是呢
Having affection and faith,
这要论有情有义
the Third Princess is an excellent woman.
三公主才是女中豪杰
I'm wondering
各位今日找我
why you're here.
有何贵干
Can you tell us
还请少君夫人教教我们
how you tamed your man?
驭夫之术吧
It's spread everywhere Young Master washed your feet.
少君给您洗脚的事情都传遍了
As women, we were told to follow Three Obedience and Four Virtues,
女人嘛 嘴上说三从四德
but actually, we hope
谁心里不希望反过来
men can listen to us.
男人样样都听自己的
In my opinion,
要我说啊
you're living a happy life.
还是少君夫人这种日子舒坦
Young Master obeys you in every way.
少君对您言听计从的
I'm so envious.
小人心生羡慕
I hope you can give me some good advice.
还望少君夫人不吝赐教
If I find a good husband in the future,
来日小人觅得良婿
I'm sure to pay you back.
必当涌泉相报
Please forgive me for being gossipy.
小人多嘴了
What does it mean to tame your man?
什么是驭夫
Let him obey you in every way and do everything as you like?
让男人言听计从 当牛做马
No.
不对
That's not real equality.
这不是真正的平等
Actually, to learn how to tame your man,
今天你们想了解的驭夫之术
you should learn to manage yourself first.
其实就是驭己之术
Manage myself?
驭己
As women,
女人啊
we need to learn how to stay true to ourselves,
要懂得去做真正的自己
how to add value to ourselves
为自己创造价值
and how to increase our husbands' value.
为夫君创造价值
Then they'll cherish and respect you.
这样他才会懂得珍惜你 尊重你
If you love a man,
那 你爱一个人呢
it doesn't mean
并不是一厢情愿地
you need to rely on him and serve him
去依赖他 服侍他
to get what you want from him.
他才会给你你想要的东西
In a relationship,
夫妻二人相处
you need to
无论男女
learn to manage yourself
都要懂得去经营自己
so that he understands
让对方明白
the importance of
你的存在对于对方来讲
your existence.
十分地宝贵
In this case, he can't do without you.
自然 也就离不开你了
It makes sense.
有道理 有道理 有道理
Unbelievable.
这谁信啊
I've become a relationship expert.
这我都变成情感专家了
If I told that actor surnamed Han about it,
要把这事给姓韩那影帝说
he'd never believe it.
谁信呢
I see.
我明白了
To put it simply, we need to play hard-to-get.
说白了 就是得吊着
We need to learn to lose temper.
得学会发脾气
We need to claim credit when necessary.
该邀功的时候 别客气
Playing the woman, shedding tears or making a scene.
撒娇眼泪治不好
They all work.
样样都管用
Make sure he's afraid of you.
让他怕你
Right.
对 对
No. You're wrong.
不不不 不对 不对
What are you talking about? Wrong.
说什么呢 不对
It's not like that.
不是这个意思
Rewrite it.
重来
Tear your notes.
笔记撕掉 撕掉 撕掉
Let's get started.
开席吧
I don't know
我家那口子
what's happened to my wife.
最近也不知道怎么回事
She often gave me her attitude recently.
鼻子不是鼻子 眼不是眼
She found fault with everything.
处处挑刺
Someone might have seduced her
不知道受了谁的蛊惑
into getting a job.
非要出去找份差事
She's driving everyone crazy.
弄得全家都不得安宁
Same here.
我家里也是
My wife said she needed to go back to her parental home.
天天闹着回娘家
She wants to learn from women of Huayuan
还要向花垣学习
and wouldn't come back if I don't wash her feet.
不给洗脚 不再回来
Come on. Shuo.
来 烁儿
The two of us
你我父子二人
haven't drunk together for a long time.
许久没有一起喝酒了
Let's drink till we drop today.
今天一定不醉不归
Here you are.
来
Qianqian,
芊芊
Shuo told me
听烁儿说
you often participated in political affairs in Huayuan
你在花垣城时经常参与政务
and made lots of achievements.
且业绩颇丰
What do you think
那不如你来说说
those guys should do
刚刚你这几位叔伯的矛盾
with their wives' problems?
该如何调解啊
I'd like to ask you
想问在座的长辈
who manages household affairs in your family.
家里的家务谁来操持
My wife.
我家夫人呀
Who brings up children?
孩子谁来养育
Who takes care of your parents?
父母谁来照顾
Have you ever thought about that?
那你们有没有想过
Your wife is like
你们家的夫人就像是
a servant that has to
伺候你们的丫鬟
take care of you,
照顾孩子的乳母
your children and your parents.
服侍父母的仆人
It seems she stays at home and doesn't need to work,
看似一个人在家里享清闲
but actually,
实则上是一个人
she holds three posts simultaneously.
做了三个人的活儿
Everyone,
那在座的各位叔伯
have you ever said to your wife,
有没有对自己家夫人说过一句
"Thank you for what you've done.
谢谢 辛苦了
What should I do without you?"
没有你我可怎么办
We've never said
我们不曾对家里的
those words
管家 厨子 仆役
to our stewards, cooks or servants.
说这样的话呀
Do you mean
那你的意思就是说
you just consider your wife
你们的夫人也就像管家 仆人
as your steward and servant?
是一样的喽
Ridiculous. This is sophistry.
荒唐 这是诡辩
Young Master even washed her feet.
少君还给她洗脚呢
When all goes to all,
说到底
women can only do those things.
女人也只能做这些东西了
What else could they do?
除此之外 还能做什么
No.
不对
Women can do housework at home
女人可以在家里操持家务
and also handle political affairs
也可以在外跟男人一样
in court.
处理政务
You're arrogant.
好大的口气呀
Let me test you.
那我来考考你
According to census data gathered by Ministry of Statistics,
司户统计近些年的出生人口
the birth rate has been decreasing.
发现人口逐渐下降
To figure out why...
究其原因
It's because something has changed about marriage, right?
是男女婚姻出现了问题 对不对
Women began to divorce and remarry
女子开始和离和改嫁
and some even chose to always stay single,
甚至有些人不成亲
which caused declining birth rates
导致生育下降
and less young men.
青年男子减少
Do you know why it happened?
那大家知道是为什么这样吗
Men in Xuanhu City consider themselves always right
玄虎城男子 自以为是
and make decisions
不问对方喜好
without asking their partners' opinions.
就擅作主张
Bluntly, it's male chauvinism.
说白了 就是大男子主义
They want you to do everything as they say.
做什么 说什么都得听他的
Nobody will love a man like that.
这样的男子 谁会喜欢
In my opinion,
依我看
it's you women that are making trouble.
就是你们这群女人在搞事情
Men of Xuanhu are handsome and highly esteemed.
我们玄虎男子相貌堂堂
Nobody won't like us.
谁不喜欢
In the future, anyone aged 16 or above
以后 凡超过十六岁未到婚嫁的
will get a fine if they're single.
都要交罚金
A fine?
罚金
Getting taxed for being single?
单身税
The problem is still unsolved in this case.
可这也解决不了问题啊
If it doesn't work,
交税不够
then just imprison them.
那 不嫁人就直接关起来
Absurd.
荒唐
Is the current situation caused
出现现在的情况
by women?
是女人的问题吗
Obviously, it's caused by men.
这分明就是男人的问题啊
Instead of thinking about
你们不想想
how to change men,
如何去改变男人的问题
you blame everything on women.
反而把责任全部怪在女人身上
Interesting.
有趣
In your opinion,
依你说
what to do?
那该怎么办
Forget about it if you can't figure it out,
想不出来就算了
lest you waste our time.
免得浪费大家时间
Allow people of Xuanhu to marry people of Huayuan.
开放玄虎城与花垣城通婚
Women are superior to men in Huayuan
花垣以女子为尊
and it's the opposite in Xuanhu.
玄虎以男子为尊
The two cities have been irreconcilable since ancient times.
自古以来 两城势不两立
How could such marriages be possible?
何以通婚
Now that Xuanhu and Huayuan have been in a stalemate,
玄虎 花垣两城僵持
people in both cities have been influenced.
两城的人民也受到了影响
In the final analysis, it's about cultural difference.
说到底 就是文化差异的问题
Take "tiger" as an example.
比如说 虎
In Xuanhu City, it means "mighty and powerful".
在玄虎城是威猛权力的意思
But in Huayuan City,
可是在花垣城
it means "silly, rash and mindless".
就是傻愣愣 莽撞 没脑子的意思
What did you say?
你刚刚说什么
It began to mean "cute" in these years.
不过近两年也是有可爱的
Internally, we can
对内呢 我们可以解决
ease the decline in births.
玄虎人口下降的问题
Externally, we can
对外呢 我们可以化解两城
resolve misunderstandings between the two cities
因为文化差异矛盾
caused by cultural difference
形成的误会跟隔阂
and also exchange resources.
交换资源
Then, the common people can live and work in peace.
这样 百姓安居乐业
They'll enjoy a good and prosperous life.
生活富裕繁茂
What do you think?
怎么样
No man dares to marry a woman from Huayuan.
花垣城的女人 可不敢娶
But your wives, daughters and sisters
可你们的夫人 女儿 姐妹
want to marry men of Huayuan.
可都想嫁给花垣城的男子呢
He's smooth-tongued.
甜言蜜语型的
He's strong and brave.
威猛无比型的
He's gentle and considerate.
温柔体贴型的
He's handsome and stupid.
胸大无脑型的
There are different kinds of men. You name it.
各式品种 真是应有尽有
Girls, do you want to marry them?
姐妹们 想嫁吗
As the saying goes, a woman usurping a man's power will destroy a family.
常言道 牝鸡司晨 家必亡
It's better that women stay at home and don't work.
妇人们还是退居内室为好
So much for today.
今日到此为止吧
Father,
父亲
I think what Xiaoqian said
我觉得小千所说的
makes sense.
不无道理
Hold your tongue.
你还敢开口
I told you to get the mine.
我让你带矿回来
What did you get?
你带什么回来
Is she a mine?
她是矿吗
Can she burn?
她能烧吗
No. I can't.
烧 烧不了
Your Highness.
郡主
Please hand over your weapon.
请把您的兵器交给属下保管
These guys
这些人
don't seem to be the previous City Guards.
似乎不是往日的守城护城军
I heard the City Owner had heightened alert.
听说城主最近好像加强了防备
She selected generals and soldiers herself to be guards.
亲自点兵点将选拔的城主守卫
Will she be wary of me all her life?
难道母亲要一辈子都防着我吗
Your Highness.
郡主
It's not easy for the City Owner to call you in.
这次城主好不容易召见您
You need to be very cautious
您一会儿可要小心行事
and persuade her to forgive you.
务必哄得她原谅您
I know that.
这个我自然知道
Mother.
母亲
Explain it.
解释吧
Mother, I don't know this guy at all.
母亲 女儿根本不认识此人
He's confessed everything.
他已经全部都招了
What else do you want to say?
你还想说什么
Mother, please forgive my momentary recklessness.
请母亲原谅女儿一时鲁莽
Momentary recklessness?
一时鲁莽
Asshole.
畜生
How can you be so ruthless?
你竟然做出这种惨无人性之事
Do you know?
你知不知道
Qianqian played dead and bid farewell to me
芊芊为了给你让位
so that you can take her place.
才会与我假死诀别
She did that for me?
又是为了我
In your mind, she's right no matter what she does.
她做什么都是对的
She's always loyal and obedient.
都是忠义两全
Do you think
而我
I'm that heartless
就是一个坏事做尽
and ungrateful?
无情无义的人吗
Aren't you?
难道不是吗
Mother, you once told me,
母亲 你曾经教导我
to do something big,
成大事者必须斩断情分
we couldn't be swayed by emotions.
才能成就一番大业
I just don't want you to give yourself over to blind emotions.
我只是不想让你被情感所牵绊
I didn't want you to kill your family.
哪里是让你去杀害自己的亲人
Chen Qianqian didn't die.
陈芊芊她没有死
She's escaped to Xuanhu City.
她逃去玄虎城了
Do I have to thank you
那我倒要谢谢你
for letting her go?
放过芊芊一马了
I really didn't expect it.
我真是没想到
I treated you as my biological daughter.
当初 我把你当亲生女儿养育
But in the end,
反过来
you want to kill my own daughter.
你倒要杀了我的女儿
Do you mean
难道
I'm not your daughter?
我就不是您的女儿了吗
I treated the late Minister Pei like my sister.
我与已故裴司军交好 情同姐妹
After she died at her post that year,
当年 她以身殉职
I took you to my mansion
我念在你年幼无知 无人照顾
considering you were too young and nobody took care of you.
把你抱进了城主府
I ordered everyone to keep it a secret.
还下了封口令
Unexpectedly,
没想到
you're so wildly ambitious and dangerous.
却养出了你的狼子野心
You sent guys to kill Qianqian
你派人暗杀芊芊
because you're afraid
怕的就是日后
she may come back to take your place.
她回来抢你的城主之位
But do you know?
可你知道吗
I can issue an order now
我现在大可以就下令
to make you become Crown Princess
立你为少城主
and even the new City Owner.
也可以直接任命你为下一任城主
Then the whole Huayuan City will be yours.
整个花垣城都是你的
But look at yourself.
可你看看你现在的自己
Your virtues can't compare with your position.
你德不配位
The common people in the city
城中的百姓子民
and City Guards who followed you over the years
加上跟随你多年的护城军
don't want to listen to you.
都不愿归顺于你
Can you sleep without anxiety
这个位子
if you succeed me?
你坐得稳吗
How will you persuade me
你拿什么说服我
to entrust the whole city to you?
将这花垣之城托付于你
You also let down the late Minister Pei.
你又对得起已故的裴司军吗